Register of the Joseph William Ballantine Papers, 1909-1970.
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph William Ballantine Papers,
1909-1970
73076
Ballantine, Joseph, b. 1888.
3 manuscript boxes (1.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, notes, reports, articles, and printed matter, relating to American foreign policy in East Asia, and to the foreign policy views of Owen Lattimore.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1973.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Lattimore, Owen, 1900-; United States. Dept. of State.; East Asia.; East Asia--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--East Asia.
Biographical Note
1888 Born, Abmednaga, India
1909 Joined the U.S. Foreign Service
1930 Secretary of the American Delegation to the London Naval Conference
1944 Directed the Office of Far Eastern Affairs
1945-1947 Special Assistant to the Secretary of State
After his retirement, served with the Brookings Institution in Washington, D.C. and lectured at NYU
Series Description
- Memoirs, 1888-1970. (Box No. 1.)
  Xerox copy of a typewritten, autobiographic manuscript. (2 copies)
- Content Analysis - Writings of Owen Lattimore, 1935-1949. (Box No. 2.)
  Mimeograph copy of a digest of selected writings of O. Lattimore with commentaries by J. W. Ballantine.
- Subject File, 1909-1963. (Box No. 3.)
  Memoranda, reports, notes, and printed matter arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Speeches and Writings, 1940-1968. (Box No. 3.)
  Speeches and writings arranged alphabetically by title.
Container List
- MEMOIRS, 1888-1970 (2 copies)
  - Chapter I - An Unusual Upbringing (Box 1.)
  - Chapter II - Introduction to the Far East
  - Chapter III - Our Embassy at Tokyo
  - Chapter IV - Broadening of Experience
  - Chapter V - London Naval Conference
  - Chapter VI - Consul General at Canton
  - Chapter VII - Holidays in Southeast Asia
  - Chapter VIII - Consul General at Mukden
  - Chapter IX - Our Far Eastern Division (1937-1941)
  - Chapter X - Prelude to Pearl Harbor
  - Chapter XI - Wartime Activities
  - Chapter XII - Special Assistant to the Secretary of State
  - Chapter XIII - The Allied Military Occupation of Japan
  - Chapter XIV - At Brookings Institution
  - Chapter XVI - What Happened in Korea (1945-1954)
  - Chapter XVII - Problem of Vietnam: Some Facts and Considerations
  - Chapter XVIII - Epilogue
- CONTENT ANALYSIS - WRITINGS OF OWEN LATTIMORE, 1935-1949
  - Chiang Kai-Shek (1945-1950) (Box 2.)
  - China
    - Character of National Government (1944-1949)
    - Chinese Revolution (1935-1945)
    - Coalition Government (1944-1949)
    - Formosa (1944-1949)
    - Manchuria (1944-1949)
    - Recognition of People's Government of China in UN (1949-1950)
    - U.S. policy (1937-1943)
  - Indonesia (1944-1949)
  - Indo-China (1947, 1949, 1950)
  - Japan
    - Democratization (1946)
    - Economic and military support (1949)
    - Emperor institution (1944-1949)
    - Japanese communists (1946-1947)
    - Japanese peace settlement (1947, 1949)
    - Japanese-Soviet relations (1938)
  - Korea (1944-1949)
  - Lattimore and communism in general (1935-1950)
  - Mongolia
    - Nature of government and recognition of Mongolia and admission to UN (1944-1949)
    - Nature of government and Soviet policies (1928-1941)
    - Soviet policy in Mongolia
    - Leadership (1944-1949)
  - Sinkiang (1940, 1945, 1949)
  - Soviet foreign policy (1935, 1936, 1940, 1942, 1943)
  - Soviet Union (1938, 1943)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1909-1963
  - Amherst College. Biographical Record. Class of 1909. (1963) (Box 3.)
  - "Backdoor Diplomacy in the Pacific", Footnotes, by R. J. C. Butow
  - "Background of American Policy Regarding China" by Stanley K. Hornbeck
  - Brookings Institution - Southern University Conference. Seminar on Problems of U.S. Foreign Policy. San Antonio, Texas. April 1952. "A Political Settlement in Korea".
  - "China in Stalin's Grand Strategy" by Hu Shih (reprint, Foreign Affairs, January 1949)
  - Department of State Bulletin, Index. Vols. LV, Nos. 1410-1435 (July-December 1966).
  - Far Eastern Civilizations
  - "Mainland China - Geographic Strengths and Weaknesses" by G. Etzel Pearcy (reprint, Department of State Bulletin)
  - "Oral History" by Ann Mozley. (reprint, Historical Studies Australia and New Zealand, April 1967, Vol. 12, No. 48)
  - Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, 1961 - Reminiscences of Joseph Ballantine
  - Sino-American Amity Fund, Inc. 12th Annual Double Ten Dinner. New York. 1967. Seating List.
  - "The United Nations and Red China" (Committee of One Million)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1940-1968
  - "American Far Eastern Policy: A History Study" (lecture given on May 13, 1968 at the Center of Asian Studies, St. John's University, New York) (Box 3.)
  - "The Arts and Religion"
  - "Far Eastern Civilizations"
  - "The Future of Nationalist China" (1954)
  - "The Future of the Ryukyus" (reprint, Foreign Affairs, July 1953)
  - "The Great Power Struggle for Advantage in China"
  - "The New Japan" (VII)
  - "Scholarship and Diplomacy"
  - "Some Observations on American Foreign Policy"
  - "The United States and East Asia"
  - Miscellaneous